Finding Aid for Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics (University of Michigan) records, 1879-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics (University of Michigan) records
1879-1997
1896-1968
University of Michigan. Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics.
8729 Bimu F81 2, UBImul F81
Governing body for intercollegiate athletics at the University of Michigan. Records consist of correspondence, minutes, reports, petitions, account books, contracts, photographs, and scrapbooks relating primarily to the operation of the athletic department, including files of directors Fielding H. Yost, Herbert O. (Fritz) Crisler, and Don Canham, and athletic administrators Charles Baird and Philip G. Bartelme.
52 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records have been acquired in several accessions through the Board in Control and the Athletic Department. (Donor 1776 )
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics was formed in 1893 to assert a measure of faculty control over athletics. It assumed overall responsibility for athletic policy and financial management, but the Student Athletic Association continued to play a role in athletics until 1920. The board originally consisted of nine members; five chosen from the faculty senate by President Angell and four undergraduates, at first selected by the Board of Directors of the Athletic Association but later chosen by the student body. The Athletic Director traditionally served as secretary of the board
The Board has undergone a number of reorganizations, most notably in the period 1909-1914 and again in 1925-26. The reorganizations resulted in changes in the Boards, authority, composition and methods by which members were selected or appointed. Under the 1925/26 revisions, the board in control was an independently chartered corporation with considerable autonomy. In 1997 the board's status as a separately incorporated body. The management of the Athletic Department was brought more directly under the authority of the University President. The Board in Control was reorganized as the Advisory Board on Intercollegiate Athletics.
Papers, 1879 and 1891-1955, of the Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics of the University of Michigan [formerly the Athletic Association, include correspondence, reports, petitions, account books, contracts, and scrapbooks relating primarily to the operation of the athletic department, including files of athletic directors Fielding H. Yost and Herbert O. (Fritz) Crisler, and athletic administrators, Charles Baird and Philip G. Bartelme.
Subjects:
Canham, Don.; Athletics--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Football--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Baird, Charles, 1870-1944.; Bartelme, Philip George, 1876-1954.; Crisler, H. O. (Herbert Orin), 1899-1982.; Yost, Fielding Harris, 1871-1946.; Michigan Stadium (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan--Sports.Sports.; University of Michigan--Football.Football.
Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks.; Photographs.
- Correspondence, 1896-1955
  The Correspondence series covers the full gamut of topics relating to intercollegiate athletics at Michigan, ranging from broad policy issues to facilities construction and management, scheduling of games, relations with the conference and other schools, relations with the university administration and faculty, and requests for and complaints about tickets. The series is arranged chronologically, generally with several folders for each year.
  - 1896-1903 (Box 1)
  - 1904-1915 (Box 2)
  - 1916-1920 (Box 3)
  - 1921-May 1922 (Box 4)
  - June 1922-1923 (Box 5)
  - 1924-January 1925 (Box 6)
  - February 1925-January 1926 (Box 7)
  - February-November 1926 (Box 8)
  - December 1926-August 1927 (Box 9)
  - September 1927-March 1928 (Box 10)
  - April-November 1928 (Box 11)
  - December 1928-July 1929 (Box 12)
  - August 1929-March 1930 (Box 13)
  - April-November 1930 (Box 14)
  - December 1930-June 1931 (Box 15)
  - July 1931-January 1932 (Box 16)
  - February-August 1932 (Box 17)
  - September 1932-September 1933 (Box 18)
  - October 1933-September 1934 (Box 19)
  - October 1934-October 1935 (Box 20)
  - November 1935-March 1937 (Box 21)
  - April 1937-March 1938 (Box 22)
    (February 1938 includes notes by BIC member James Duffy on hiring of H.O. Crisler)
  - April 1938-December 1938 (Box 23)
  - January-September 1939 (Box 24)
  - October 1939-April 1940 (Box 25)
  - May-November 1940 (Box 26)
  - December 1940-November 1941 (Box 27)
  - December 1941-December 1942 (Box 28)
  - January 1943-May 1944 (Box 29)
  - June 1944-September 1945 (Box 30)
  - October 1945-September 1949 (Box 31)
  - October 1949-February 1955 (Box 32)
  - undated (Box 32)
- Annual reports
  The Annual Reports series, 1911/12-1967/68, consists of the board's report to the Regents. It usually included a summary of the year's activities and finances and overviews of facilities construction and renovation and significant personnel changes.
  - 1911/12-1967/68 (Box 32)
    (includes original reports and photocopies of printed reports from Regents Proceedings and other sources)
- Topical files, 1879-, circa 1954
  The Topical files series (13 linear feet) (32 linear feet) is an alphabetically arrange subject file. The earliest file is the articles of incorporation of the Athletic Association in 1879, but the bulk of the series from the 1920s to 1954 covering the tenures of athletic directors Fielding H, Yost and Herbert O Crisler.
  - Athletic Association
    - Articles of association, 1879 (Box 33)
    - Constitution, 1891 (Box 33)
    - Correspondence and minutes, 1929-1940 (Box 33)
  - Auditors, 1941-1946 (Box 33)
  - 1941-1954 (Box 33)
  - Baseball
    - General, 1944-1954 (Box 33)
    - Town baseball report (Box 33)
    - Contracts, 1936-1941 (Box 33)
  - Basketball
    - General, 1937-1955 (Box 33)
    - Contracts, 1936-1941 (Box 33)
  - Bell, Margaret, 1941-1949 (Box 33)
  - Boxing, 1943-1954 (Box 33)
  - Building and grounds, 1942-1946 (Box 33)
  - Buildings (athletic), Use of, 1944-1947 (Box 33)
  - Byers, Walter (NCAA Ex. Dir.) (Box 33)
  - Coaching schools, 1938-1948 (Box 33)
  - Commencement exercises, 1927-1931 (Box 33)
  - Commissioner of Intercollegiate Conference, 1928 (Box 33)
  - Committee on Non-Athletic Organizations, 1913 (Box 33)
  - Complimentary ticket lists (Box 33)
  - Conference medals, 1944-1952 (Box 33)
  - Emergency training, 1943 (Box 33)
  - Engagements accepted, 1948-1951/52 (Box 33)
  - Engagements accepted, 1952/53-1953/54 (Box 34)
  - Engagements not accepted [sample], 1948-1954 (Box 34)
  - Enlistment (military) information (Box 34)
  - Field House and Ferry Field, 1942-1953 (Box 34)
  - Financial miscellanea, 1914-1929 (Box 34)
  - Football
    - Team lists and related material, 1939; 1941-1945 (Box 34)
    - Program material, 1942-1945 (Box 34)
    - Carnegie report on football, 1927-1931 (Box 34)
    - Charity game controversy, 1931 (Box 34)
    - Contracts, 1936-1940 (Box 34)
    - Detroit, University of (proposed game for unemployed), 1930; 6 folders (Box 34)
    - Freshmen Rule (Suspension of rule during World War II), 1942 (Box 35)
    - UM's return to Intercollegiate Football conference, 1913 (Box 35)
    - "Commercialism" charges, 1951 (Box 35)
    - George Jewett (Black football player) (Box 35)
    - All-American players (Box 35)
    - Schedules, 1944-1954 (Box 35)
    - History of Football, 1926-1939 (Box 35)
    - "B" Team Football Games, 1946-1947 (Box 35)
    - Financial reports to the conference (Box 35)
    - U-M-Army Football Game, 1946 (Box 35)
  - Gasoline rationing and transportation (WWII) (Box 35)
  - Golf
    - Contracts (Box 35)
    - Western Conference Golf Championship, 1942 (Box 35)
  - Golf course (Box 35)
  - Hockey contracts (Box 35)
  - Hockey Rink construction, 1950 (Box 35)
  - Ice rink, 1943-1954 (Box 35)
  - Intercollegiate Athletics, Department of
    - Report, 1921-1925 (Box 35)
  - Intercollegiate Conference, 1923-1928; 1940-1942 (Box 35)
  - "M" men (Box 35)
  - Minnesota, University of (Box 35)
  - Movies, 1940-1954 (Box 35)
  - National Collegiate Athletic Association, 1941-1953 (Box 36)
  - National Outdoor Recreation Conference, 1924-1926 (Box 36)
  - New releases, 1944-1945 (Box 36)
  - Notre Dame, 1910-1945 (Box 36)
  - Olympics, 1947-1954 (Box 36)
  - Pennsylvania, University of, 1944 (Box 36)
  - Physical Education and Athletics, Department of
    - By-laws, 1941-1942 (Box 36)
    - General (Box 36)
  - Post-war physical program (Box 36)
  - Press box staff, 1943-1944 (Box 36)
  - Price Administration, Office of, 1943 (Box 36)
  - Questionnaires and surveys (Army and Navy)
    - 1942-1943 (Box 36)
  - Radio
    - Miscellaneous, 1945-1953 (Box 36)
    - Broadcasting, 1935 (Box 36)
    - Programs, 1938-1954 (Box 36)
    - Upper Peninsula, 1948-1952 (Box 36)
    - WUOM, 1948-1953 (Box 36)
  - Recommendations for positions [sample], 1943-1950 (Box 36)
  - Regents' communications, 1919-1941 (Box 36)
  - Requests for positions on staff [sample], 1946-1954 (Box 36)
  - Ruthven, Alexander, 1941-1946 (Box 36)
  - Scholarships, 1941 (Box 36)
  - Swimming
    - General, 1926-1955 (Box 36)
    - Contracts, 1936-1940 (Box 36)
    - Western Conference Swimming Meet, 1942-1943 (Box 36)
    - NCAA Swim Meets, 1944-1945 (Box 36)
  - Tennis
    - General, 1941-1955 (Box 36)
    - Contracts, 1935-1941 (Box 36)
  - Tennis Courts, 1941-1953 (Box 36)
  - Ticket affidavits, 1934-1935 (Box 37)
  - Track
    - General, 1941-1954 (Box 37)
    - Contracts, 1936-1941 (Box 37)
    - Track meet records, 1879-1898 (Box 37)
    - Programs, 1900-1952; 2 folders (Box 37)
  - University War Board, 1942-1943 (Box 37)
  - Wisconsin, University of, 1944-1953 (Box 37)
  - Wrestling
    - General, 1943-1954 (Box 37)
    - Contracts, 1934-1941 (Box 37)
  - Yost sketch: "A Day with Professor Yost" (Box 37)
  - Miscellaneous Papers (other than correspondence)
    - 1903-1939 (Box 37)
    - 1940-1953, undated (Box 38)
  - N.C.A.A. Television Committee
    - 1948-1953 (Box 38)
    - 1953-1955, 9 folders (Box 39)
  - Board in Control of Physical Education (Box 39)
  - Minutes and related materials, 1935-1941; 14 folders (Box 39)
  - Ann Arbor Railroad (Box 39)
  - Baseball Grandstand Construction reports, circa 1950 (Box 39)
  - Football
    - Prospects, 1930 (Box 39)
    - Schedule, 1928-1931 (Box 39)
    - "B" football (Box 39)
    - 1928 (Box 39)
    - Data on teams,., 1897-1903 (Box 39)
    - Clippings, 1936-1937 (Box 39)
  - Golf Course Club House (progress reports, ), 1947-1951 (Box 39)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 39)
  - Program Sales, 1940 (Box 40)
  - National Youth Administration, 1942-1943 (Box 40)
  - Michigan High School Athletic Association, 1932 (Box 40)
  - Football Scouting Reports, 1933-1937 (Box 40)
  - Boys Week, 1924; 1 volumes (Box 40)
  - Petitions re: the naming of Yost Field House, 1 volumes (Box 40)
  - Physical Education Departments' Reports, etc., undated; 1 volumes (Box 40)
  - Report of the Department of Intercollegiate Athletics, 1921-1925; 1 volumes (Box 40)
  - Miscellaneous legal papers (Box 40)
  - Account books of Charles Baird, 1893-1905; 14 volumes (Box 40)
  - Record books (Athletic Association), 5 volumes (Box 40)
  - Articles by Fielding Yost, 4 volumes (Box 41)
  - Scouting Reports, 1920-1923; 4 volumes (Box 41)
  - Scouting Reports, 1920-1923; 3 volumes (Box 42)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1921-1923; 6 volumes (Box 42)
  - Football notes, undated; 1 volumes (Box 42)
  - Mailing Lists, 1940; 1 volumes (Box 43)
  - Miscellaneous Notes on Football, 1921-1928; 10 volumes (Box 43)
  - Miscellaneous Notes on Football, 1921-1928; 11 volumes (Box 44)
  - Miscellaneous Notes on Football, 1921-1928; 1 volumes (Box 45)
  - Reports and Resolutions of the Board in Control of Athletics, 1924-1928 (Box 45)
  - Scrapbooks, 4 volumes (Box 45)
- Michigan Stadium
  The Michigan Stadium series (1.2 linear feet) contains documentation of the planning, financing and construction of the stadium. It includes correspondence, reports, promotional material, construction documents (though not blueprints) and records of bond sales and several original bonds.
  - Construction bonds
    - Proposed bond issue (Box 46)
    - Sales (Box 46)
    - Tax exempt status (Box 46)
    - Donors
      - 1927-1930 (Box 46)
      - 1939-1940 (Box 46)
    - Interest, 1928 (Box 46)
    - Payment of bonds (Box 46)
    - Retirement, 1936-1940 (Box 46)
  - Excavation bids, 1926 (Box 46)
  - Construction bids, 1927 (Box 46)
  - Osborn Engineering Company estimates, 1926-1927 (Box 46)
  - Stadium seats (Box 46)
  - Stadium drain, 1926-1927 (Box 46)
  - Stadium fences, 1927 (Box 46)
  - Jacob Bros. (concessionaire),1948-1953 (Box 46)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 46)
  - Stadium Design Information (Box 46)
    (photos and articles on other athletic stadia)
  - Stadium Bond papers (Box 51)
    (includes an original bond)
- Land Deed and Mortgage Papers
  The Land deeds series includes deeds and related records for property acquired for construction of various Athletic Department facilities including Ferry Field, Michigan Stadium, and the golf course.
  - Ferry Field (Box 46)
    (Includes a listing of deeds for Ferry Field, Michigan Stadium and Golf Course parcels)
  - Ferry Field, Linn/Felch Farm (South of Ferry Field) (Box 46)
  - Ferry Field, Westgate parcel (Box 46)
  - Michigan Stadium (Box 46)
  - Papers relating to Michigan Stadium land deed (Box 46)
  - Golf Course (Box 46)
- Reports and Miscellaneous files
  The Reports and Miscellaneous Files series (1.2 linear feet) includes a variety of reports dating from 1926 to 1942, including a "Ten Year Report, 1921-1931", covering Fielding Yost's first ten years as athletic director, and three volumes of financial journals which include a record of capital expenditures on athletic facilities through 1968.
  - Football games, 1928; 1930 (Box 46)
  - Ten Year Report, 1921-1931 (Box 46)
  - Report
    - July 1, 1926-September 1, 1927 (Box 46)
    - July 1, 1926-July 1, 1931 (Box 46)
  - Report "A", 1928 (Box 46)
  - Report
    - February 1, 1931 (Box 46)
    - July 1-November 17, 1932 (Box 46)
    - July 1-December 1932 (Box 46)
    - December 1, 1942 (Box 46)
  - Account code (Box 46)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 46)
  - Reports (general) (Box 46)
  - Minutes of the Intercollegiate Conference, Faculty Representatives, 1980-1986; 2 volumes (Box 51)
    (taken from the papers of Donald Canham)
  - Intercollegiate Conference and National Collegiate Athletic Association published materials (Box 51)
  - Financial journals, 3 volumes (Box 51)
  - Sports Service Building papers (Box 51)
  - Patent materials (swimming timing device) (Box 51)
  - Stock Certificate of Intercollegiate Conference Athletic Association (Box 51)
- Photographs
  Photographs consists primarily of football and baseball team photos and a 1923 photo album of the dedication of Yost Field House. Included in the album are pictures of the Field House Dedication and the football game against the Quanitco Marines team, photos from the 1923 Ohio state game, posed shots of players from 1922-1923, and an action photo from the 1902 Minnesota football game. Other items of note include an outsize, panorama of action from the 1902 Tournament of Roses game (All of the football team photos and the Tournament of Roses photo are online in the Bentley Image Bank)
  - Photograph Album, 1 volumes (Box 45)
    (Includes Dedication of the Yost Field House, 1923 Marines vs. Mich. November 10, 1923, 1902 Minnesota game; miscellaneous)
  - Baseball (team photo ca. 1889) (Box 46)
    (seal also box 47)
  - Football
    - Game photos (1920s ?), 2 folders (Box 46)
      (see also Box 47)
    - Practice photos (1920s ?) (Box 46)
    - Rose Bowl Game, 1902 (Box 46)
    - Team photos, 1878; 1941 (Box 46)
  - Joe Parker's Place (Box 46)
  - Office scenes (Box 46)
  - Baseball, team photo, 1886-1900 (Box 47)
  - Football
    - Game photos, 1911; 1920s (Box 47)
    - Team photos
      - 1901-1920 (Box 47)
      - 1921-1940 (Box 47)
    - Rose Bowl Game, 1902 (Folder UBImul)
    - Team photos, 1887 (Folder UBImul)
- Board in Control Minutes, agenda and related material
  The Board in Control minutes series consist of a complete run of minutes, 1896-1997 and meeting agendas, 1968-1989 (Don Canham's tenure as Athletic Director.)
  - Minutes
    - 1893-1927, 5 volumes (Box 48)
    - 1927-1973, 4 volumes; 1 folders (Box 49)
    - 1971-1992, 8 volumes (Box 50)
    - 1993-June 1997 (Box 52)
  - Agendas of Board meetings (taken from the papers of Donald Canham, 1967-1988 (Box 52)
  - Meeting transcript, December 10, 1910 (Box 52)
    (mainly concerning question of return to conference)